A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 1994; 1998-2006
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education 1994; 1998-2006
The Library of Virginia
43510 and 44681
61.72 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Secretary of Education, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. Accession 4233 transferred 5 December 2005 and accessioned on 6 December 2006; Accession 42399 transferred on 18 January 2006 and accessioned on 19 January 2006; both accessions combined into one body of records under accession 43510 on 2 November 2007.
Additional Secretary of Education records from the Warner administration were transferred to the Library as part of the Kaine administration transfer in 2010. Accession 44681 was transferred and accessioned on 12 January 2010.
Accruals
Additional Secretary of Education records from the Warner administration were transferred to the Library as part of the Kaine administration collection in January 2010.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
The Secretary of Education assists the Governor in the development and implementation of the state's education policy. The secretary provides guidance to 16 colleges and universities, the Virginia Community College System, five higher education and research centers, the Department of Education, the state-supported museums, and other agencies in the Education Secretariat. All secretaries are appointed by the governor and serve at his will.
During the Administration of Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006) the Secretary of Education directed policy for education programs that involve multiple agencies including: Department of Education, Library of Virginia, Frontier Culture Museum of Virginia, Gunston Hall, Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Science Museum of Virginia and Virginia Commission for the Arts. While Virginia's Colleges and Universities are semi-autonomous, the Secretary of Education also plays a role in directing state policy for: Virginia Community Colleges, Christopher Newport University, George Mason University, James Madison University, Longwood University, Mary Washington University, Norfolk State University, Old Dominion University, Radford University, Richard Bland College, University of Virginia, Virginia Commonwealth University, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia State University, Virginia Tech, College of William and Mary, Roanoke Higher Education Center, Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center, and State Council of Higher Education.
Some of Governor Warner's education initiatives were: Higher Education restructuring, Education for a Lifetime, and Partnership for Achieving Successful Schools (PASS).
On 17 December 2002, Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named Dr. Belle S. Wheelan as Secretary of Education. Since 1998 Wheelan had served as President of Northern Virginia Community College. Previously, Wheelen served as President of Central Virginia Community College in Lynchburg, Provost of the Portsmouth campus of Tidewater Community College, Dean of Student Services at Thomas Nelson Community College in Hampton, and Director of Developmental Education and Director of Academic Support Services at San Antonio College in Texas. Wheelan served until June 2005 when she became president of the Commission on Colleges of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. She was succeeded by her deputy, Peter Blake. Blake served until the end of the Warner administration in January 2006.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Education, Records, are housed in one hundred seventy-nine (179 boxes). The collection is arranged into seven (7) series. Series have been designated for: I. Cabinet Meeting Records, 2002-2005; II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation - Assigned State Agencies, 1998-2005; III. Constituent Correspondence, 2002-2005; IV. Office of the Secretary, 2002-2006; V. Planning and Budget Files, 2001-2005; VI. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2001-2006; and VII. Additional Records. These records include agendas, agreements, articles, briefings, correspondence, e-mails, grants, handouts, legislation, lists, memorandums, minutes, notes, presentations, press releases, reports, resumes, speeches, studies, surveys and files by subject. These records document the work of the Secretary of Education under Governor Mark R. Warner. The most significant and voluminous material documents the development and implementation of the various educational initiatives of the Warner Administration including: Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Board Appointments, Governor's Higher Education Summit, expanding College and University Research, Higher Education Restructuring, Education for a Lifetime Initiative (Early Childhood Initiative, Path to Industry Certification, Career and Technical Education, and School Efficiency Reviews), Governor's Partnership for Achieving Successful Schools (PASS), Commission to Review, Study, and Reform Educational Leadership, and High School Reform.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Cabinet Meeting Records, 2002-2005
II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Assigned State Agencies, 1998-2005
Subseries A. Board Appointments, 2002-2005
Subseries B. Higher Education and State Agencies, 1998-2005
Subseries C. Continuity of Operations Planning (COOP), 2003-2005
Subseries D. Small, Women-owned and Minority Business (SWAM), 2003-2005
III. Constituent Correspondence, 2002-2005
IV. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2006
Subseries A. Correspondence of Secretary Belle Wheelan (2002-2005) and Secretary Peter Blake (2005-2006), 2002-2006
Subseries B. Files of Sarah Finley, Deputy Secretary of Education, 2001-2005
V. Planning and Budget Files, 2001-2005
VI. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2001-2006
Subseries A. Higher Education, 2001-2006
Subseries B. Education for a Lifetime Initiative, 2002-2005
Subseries C. The Governor's Partnership for Achieving Successful Schools (PASS), 2002-2005
Subseries D. Commission to Review, Study and Reform Educational Leadership, 2002-2005
Subseries E. Teachers, 2002-2005
Subseries F. High School Reform, 2004-2005
Subseries G. Healthy Virginians, 2003-2005
VII. Additional Records, 1994; 1998; 2000-2006
Subseries A. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2006
Subseries B. Special Project and Studies, 1994; 1998; 2000-2005
Subseries C. Legislative Files, 2002-2004
Subseries D. Weekly Reports, 2002-2005
Contents List
- I. Cabinet Meeting, 2002-2005., Extent: 0.70 cu. ft. (Box 1-2)
  The Cabinet Meeting Records series is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged chronologically. Series contains agenda's, handwritten meeting notes, and materials collected and/or presented at the governor's cabinet meetings by the Secretary of Education (Dr. Belle S. Wheelan, 2002-2005 and Peter Blake, 2005) and any annotations to the material made by the Secretary. There are not extant notes for every cabinet meeting. See Governor Mark R. Warner, Executive Office, Cabinet Meeting Journals for additional cabinet meeting information (accession 42621).
  - 18 January 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 28 January 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4 February 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 27 February 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 4 March 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 8 March 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 25 March 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1 April 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 8 April 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 15 April 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 22 April 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 29 April 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 13 May 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 20 May 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 3 June 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 10 June 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 17 June 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 24 June 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1 July 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 22 July 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 12 August 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 19 August 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 26 August 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 9 September 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 16 September 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 23 September 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 30 September 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 7 October 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 21 October 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 28 October 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 4 November 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 25 November 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2 December 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 9 December 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 16 December 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 6 January 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 13 January 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 20 January 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 27 January 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 3 February 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 21 February 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 3 March 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 10 March 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 17 March 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 7 April 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 14 April 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 28 April 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 9 June 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 16 June 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 23 June 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 30 June 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 21 July 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 8 September 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 15 September 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 29 September 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 6 October 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 20 October 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 27 October 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 17 November 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1 December 2003 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 5 January 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 12 January 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 15 March 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 22 March 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 12 April 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 7 June 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 14 June 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 24 June 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 12 July 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2 August 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 20 September 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 4 October 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 6 December 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 20 December 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2 May 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 23 May 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 6 June 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 11 July 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 25 July 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 1998-2005., Extent: 11.03 cubic feet (32 boxes). (Box 3-30)
  Series is arranged into four subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Board Appointments; B. Community Colleges, Universities and State Agencies; C. Continuity of Operation Planning; and D. SWAM. This series documents the correspondence sent and received by the office to and from state agencies assigned to the Secretary of Education, including colleges and universities. The series consists of agendas, agreements, correspondence, handouts, memorandum, notes, presentations, reports, and resumes.
  - Subseries II.A. Board Appointments, 2002-2005., Extent: 1.75 cubic feet. (Box 3-7)
    This subseries is housed in five boxes and is arranged alphabetically by the name of board. Subseries contains correspondence, memorandums, nominations, applications and resume material for, from, and about citizens who were appointed to agency and college and university boards within the Education secretariat by Governor Mark R. Warner. Also included are board profiles, which explain the purpose and goals of the boards, and the number, name, and make-up of board members.
    In addition, this series contain records related to the Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Board Appointments. Created by Governor Warner's Executive Order 8 on 7 February 2002, the Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Board Appointments reviewed potential appointees to the governing boards of Virginia's institutions of higher education, the Virginia Community College Board, and the State Council of Higher Education. The review process criteria was based on merit, experience, sound judgment, and proven leadership. The Commission had seven members appointed by the Governor: Marshall Acuff, the chairman of the Board of Directors of the Association of the Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges; Joshua P. Darden, former University of Virginia rector; James B. Murray, Jr., former College of William and Mary rector; Paul Torgersen, former Virginia Tech president; Reginald Brown, former member of the Business Advisory Board of George Mason University; Grace Harris, former Virginia Commonwealth University provost; and Lovey Hammel, chairwoman of the George Mason University Foundation Board. The Secretary of Education (Dr. Belle S. Wheelan) and Secretary of the Commonwealth (Anita Rimler) served non-voting members of the Commission. The Commission records in this series are Dr. Wheelan's. This series provides information about the appointment process, as well as background information on those chosen to serve.
    - A.L. Philpott Manufacturing Extension Partnership (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Christopher Newport University (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - College of William and Mary (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Education Commission of the States (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - George Mason University (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - James Madison University (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - James Monroe Law Office Museum (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Library of Virginia (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Longwood University (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Mary Washington College (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Old Dominion University (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Radford University (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Roanoke Higher Education Authority (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - University of Virginia (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Community College System (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Military Institute (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Virginia State University (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, Board Overviews (part one) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, Board Overviews (part two) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 12 March 2002 Meeting (part one) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 12 March 2002 Meeting (part two) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 12 March 2002 Meeting (part three) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 7 May 2002 Meeting (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 3 June 2002 Meeting (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Governor's Advisory Commission on Higher Education Appointments, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.B. Higher Education and State Agencies, 1998-2005., Extent: 9.10 cubic feet. (Box 8-29)
    This subseries is housed in 26 boxes and is further subdivided by Higher Education, State Agencies and Other and alphabetical there under. Subseries contains agendas, agreements, correspondence, handouts, memorandums, notes, presentations, and reports.
    Notable documents filed under Higher Education include: background information on Higher Education Summit, 7-8 October 2002 including Steering Committee meeting materials, 31 May 2002 (B8, F1-2); documents related to Virginia Tech's 2003 decision to end any preferences in admission or hiring including a 14 March 2003 letter from Dr. Wheelan to Attorney General Jerry Kilgore; a 19 March 2003 e-mail from Peter Blake to Dr. Wheelan analyzing the Attorney General Office's response to Dr. Wheelan's 14 March letter; and talking points for Governor Warner for a 4 June 2003 interview with Virginian Pilot reporter Phil Walzer (B8, F3). The Accord between the Commonwealth of Virginia and the United States Department of Education's Office of Civil Rights to implement certain program and facilities improvements at Norfolk State University is documented (B10, F8 and B11, F1); and State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV) agenda books for the 10 May 2005 (B18, F4) and 19 July 2005 (B18, F2) meetings.
    Notable documents filed under State Agencies include: Department of Education Briefing Notebooks prepared by Jo Lynne DeMary, Superintendent of Public Instruction for Suzette Denslow and Sarah Finley of Governor Warner's Transition Office, dated 7 December 2001 (B20-B21); 2003 Legislative Proposals for the Department of Education, 6 September 2002 (B23, F1); and materials related to Governor Warner's Education Roundtable, 24 January 2002 (includes agendas, notes, and handouts). (B23, F5)
    - Higher Education
      - Higher Education Summit, 7-8 October 2002 (part one) (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Higher Education Summit, 7-8 October 2002 (part two) (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 2001-2005 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Christopher Newport University, 2001-2005 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Eastern Virginia Medical School, 2002-2004 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - George Mason University, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - George Mason University, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - George Mason University, 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - George Mason University, 2002-2005 (part four) (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - George Mason University, 2002-2005 (part five) (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - George Washington University, 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Hampton University, 2002-2004 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - James Madison University, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Longwood University, 2002-2004 (part one) (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Longwood University, 2002-2004 (part two) (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Mary Baldwin College, 2003-2005 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Mary Washington College, 2002-2005 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Norfolk State University, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Norfolk State University, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Old Dominion University, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Old Dominion University, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Radford University, 2002-2005 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Richard Bland College, 2002-2004 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Strayer University, 2003-2004 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part four) (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part five) (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part six) (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - University of Virginia, 2002-2005 (part seven) (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - University of Virginia Medical Center, 2002-2003 (part one) (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - University of Virginia Medical Center, 2002-2003 (part two) (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - University of Virginia's College at Wise, 2002-2005 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2002-2005 (part four) (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Virginia Community College System (VCCS), 2002-2005 (part five) (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Military Institute (VMI), 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Virginia Military Institute (VMI), 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Virginia State University (VSU), 2002-2005 (part one) (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Virginia State University (VSU), 2002-2005 (part two) (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Virginia State University (VSU), 2002-2005 (part three) (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Virginia State University (VSU), 2002-2005 (part four) (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Tech, 2001-2005 (part one) (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Virginia Tech, 2001-2005 (part two) (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - College of William and Mary, 2002-2005 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Blue Ridge Community College, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Germanna Community College, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College, 2002-2003 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - John Tyler Community College, 2002, 2004 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Northern Virginia Community College, 2003-2004 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Southside Virginia Community College, 2002-2003 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Thomas Nelson Community College, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Tidewater Community College, 2003-2005 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - Private Colleges, 2002-2005 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Council of Independent Colleges in Virginia, 2002-2005 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - College Presidents Salaries, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Roanoke Higher Education Center, 2002-2005 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - The Southern Virginia Higher Education Center, 2005 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Southwest Virginia Higher Education Center, 2004 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with Out-of-State Colleges, 2002-2003, 2005 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Report on College Admission Process, 2002-2004 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Education Commission of the States, Higher Education Policy Audit, 2003 (part one) (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Education Commission of the States, Higher Education Policy Audit, 2003 (part two) (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part one) (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part two) (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part three) (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part four) (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part five) (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part six) (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part seven) (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part eight) (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part nine) (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part ten) (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - State Council of Higher Education for Virginia (SCHEV), 2001-2005 (part eleven) (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Council of Presidents, 2003-2005 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Tuition Assistant Grant (TAG), 2002, 2004 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - State Agencies
      - Department of Education, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Department of Education, Briefing Book, 2001 (part one) (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Department of Education, Briefing Book, 2001 (part two) (Box 20, Folder 3)